Guide to the Memory Project Oral History collection, 2009-2016 | 民间记忆计划口述史 RL.10171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
The Memory Project Oral History collection | 民间记忆计划口述史
2009-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.10171
2959 Gigabytes
The Memory Project Oral History collection comprises digital video recordings and written supporting documentation of interviews spanning 2009 to 2016. The interviews were conducted by filmmakers associated with the Work Station, a film studio run by Wu Wenguang in Caochangdi, Beijing, China. Memory Project interviews were conducted with Chinese people about mid-20th century rural life, primarily experiences during the Great Famine (1958-1961), but also the Land Reform and Collectivization (1949-1953), the Great Leap Forward (1958-1960), the Four Cleanups Movement (1964), and the Cultural Revolution (1966-1976). Wu's studio in suburban Beijing, known as the Work Station, is the home for this project. More than 150 young filmmakers have joined the project, and since 2010 they have visited 246 villages in 20 provinces and interviewed more than 1,100 elderly villagers. These filmmakers, many of whom returned to their families' rural hometowns, developed new intergenerational relationships with elderly relatives. During the process of interviewing the villagers, they reconciled the official history taught in schools with each family's experiences.
Scope and Contents
The Memory Project Oral History collection comprises digital video recordings and written supporting documentation of interviews spanning 2009 to 2016. The interviews were conducted by filmmakers associated with the Work Station, a film studio run by Wu Wenguang in Caochangdi, Beijing, China. Memory Project interviews were conducted with Chinese people about mid-20th century rural life, primarily experiences during the Great Famine (1958-1961), but also the Land Reform and Collectivization (1949-1953), the Great Leap Forward (1958-1960), the Four Cleanups Movement (1964), and the Cultural Revolution (1966-1976). The interviews show regional variations in famine experiences and rural culture. They add intimate detail and humanity to the story of the deaths and starvation of millions of Chinese, providing a unique perspective on the unofficial history of the Great Famine.
Due to the geographic scope and rural focus of the Memory Project, the interviews are frequently conducted in regional dialects. In many cases, the filmmakers provided Chinese language transcripts. Many recordings are also accompanied by prose reflections written by the filmmakers, the text of which originally came from the Work Station blog or email communication between filmmakers. The notes and blogs written by the filmmakers and the interview footage preserve the fading memories of people who lived through the Great Famine, ensuring that their stories are not forgotten.
The interviews described in this collection guide are arranged geographically by Province and Village. While multiple filmmakers may have worked in a single province, in most cases, only a single filmmaker traveled to each village represented. Approximately 500, nearly one half, of the interviews and supporting documentation are described as of January 2021. These interviews include those conducted by Wu Wenguang 吴文光, Zhang Mengqi 章梦奇, Zou Xueping 邹雪平, Li Xinmin 李新民, Jia Nannan 贾楠楠, Luo Bing 罗兵, Lin Tao 林涛, Zhang Ping 张苹, Li Yushan 李雨珊, Guo Zhihua 郭志华, Qu Yufeng 屈玉凤, Gao Runxiang 高润香, Guo Rui 郭睿, Hu Tao 胡涛, Jia Zhitan 贾之坦, Shao Yuzhen 邵玉珍, Shu Qiao 舒侨, Wen Hui 文慧, Wu Haizhu 吴海珠, Ye Zuyi 叶祖艺, Yi Yangmin 易旸敏, and Zhang Haishen 张海深. Other interviews will be published incrementally as each filmmaker's material is arranged and described.
Most materials are available in Chinese. A smaller number of interview transcripts have been translated into English. Those interviews that have English translations are noted in the individual interview descriptions below. All digital files are available online. Videos may be played directly through this collection guide while additional text documents and transcripts can be accessed clicking links next to the embedded videos in this collection guide, or directly via Duke Digital Collections at https://repository.duke.edu/dc/memoryproject/.
Biographical / Historical
In 2010, documentary filmmaker Wu Wenguang launched the Memory Project to collect oral histories from survivors of the Great Famine that devastated rural China between 1958 and 1961. Officially known in China as the "Three Years of Natural Disasters" or "The Difficult Three-Year Period," the Great Famine caused the death of between 20 and 43 million people. More recently the project has also covered the Great Leap Forward of 1958-1960, the Land Reform and the Collectivization of 1949-1953, the Four Cleanups Movement in 1964, and the Cultural Revolution of 1966-1976.
Wu's studio in suburban Beijing, known as the Work Station, is the home for this project. More than 150 young filmmakers have joined the project, and since 2010 they have visited 246 villages in 20 provinces and interviewed more than 1,100 elderly villagers. These filmmakers, many of whom returned to their families' rural hometowns, developed new intergenerational relationships with elderly relatives. During the process of interviewing the villagers, they reconciled the official history taught in schools with each family's experiences.
Wu Wenguang was born in 1956 in Yunnan Province, China, as is considered a founding figure in Chinese independent documentary films. His other work includes Bumming in Beijing: the Last Dreamers (1990), 1966: My Time in the Red Guards (1993), At Home in the World (1995), Jiang Hu: Life on the Road (1999), Dance with Farm Workers (2002), Fuck Cinema (2005), Treating (2010), Bare Your Stuff (2010), Investigating My Father (2016), and Gao Bo between Beijing-Paris (2019).
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Memory Project Oral History collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 2013 and 2016.
China -- History -- Famine -- 1958-1962; China -- History -- Cultural Revolution -- 1966-1976; Land reform -- China -- History; China -- History -- Great Leap Forward -- 1958-1960; Land use, Rural -- China; China -- Rural conditions; Oral histories (document genre); Electronic records; Guo, Zhihua
- Beijing | 北京, 2011
  - Gaogezhuang Village | 顺义区杨镇高各庄, 2011
    Scope and Contents
    Gaogezhuang Village is located in Shunyi District, Beijing. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Shao Yuzhen.
    高各庄位于北京市顺义区杨镇。村民的录像采访人是邵玉珍。
    - Wu Shiqi | 吴士奇, 2011
      Wu Shiqi (b. 1933) is a resident of Gaogezhuang Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Wu talks about his experience during the Great Famine. Wu was driving cart for the production team in Xiaodian Village, so he did not starve at all. However, because the production team in his village needed to build a kindergarten, the east side of his house had to be demolished.
      吴士奇1933年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇高各庄村民。在这段口述中，吴老人回忆了大饥荒时期吃食堂的经历。当时吴老人在小店为生产队赶车，所以没有挨饿，但因为村里要建幼儿园，吴老人家东边的房子都给拆了。
  - Shaziying Village | 顺义区杨镇沙子营, 2011
    Shaziying Village is located in Shunyi District, Beijing. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Shao Yuzhen.
    沙子营村位于北京市顺义区杨镇。村民的录像采访人是邵玉珍。
    - Gao Yueqi | 高悦启, 2011
      Gao Yueqi (b. 1928) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. Gao joined the communist army during the Civil War. After being demobilized, he was assigned to work on finalizing the Land Reform. In this interview, Gao describes various policies during the Land Reform and how to calculate the exploitation rate for the purpose of class identification. Meanwhile, Gao points out that there were lots of physical conflicts during the Land Reform and many people were beaten to death. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      高悦启1928年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村村民，解放战争时期入伍参军，复员转业后参与土改的收尾工作。在这段口述中高老人讲述了当年土改的各项政策，如何靠计算剥削率来划定成分。据高老人回忆，土改期间打人情况严重，有些村打死不少人。
    - Lu Jiwen | 卢记文, 2010
      Lu Jiwen (b. 1945) moved to Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing in 1961 when his parents who were intellectuals but received mistreatment were sent to the countryside for reeducation. In this interview, Lu talks about the life before and after Cultural Revolution. Because most of the work points they earned by working at the production team were used to treat his mom's heart disease, they led a very poor life. His dad passed away when the Four Cleanups Movement just started and his reputation was not rehabilitated until when Cultural Revolution ended. When his mom passed away in 1966 and his four elder sisters all left home because of work or school, he and his younger brother were the only ones left at home and had to support themselves by working at the production team. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      卢记文1945年出生，1961年随父母下放到北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营劳动。在这段口述中，卢老人回忆了文革前后的生活。因为卢老人的母亲有心脏病，家里在生产队工作挣的工分都给她用来看病，所剩无几。63年大四清刚开始的时候卢老人的父亲就去世了，他的名誉一直到文革结束以后才得以恢复。66年卢老人的母亲也去世了，四个姐姐因为读书和工作的关系也已离家，家里就剩下卢老人和弟弟靠务农劳作相依为命。
    - Yin Lianrong | 尹连荣, 2011
      Yin Lianrong (b. 1941) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Yin recalls the life during and after the Great Famine. Once a pig of the Production Team in Gaogezhuang Village died, so the man who fed the livestock cooked the pig. His son ate most of the pig and was eventually stuffed to death. Because of the edible things her dad found near the reed field, Yin's family did not starve badly. When one of her kids was born, due to malnutrition, Yin did not have milk. She had to buy a goat for 5 Yuan and fed the baby with goat milk. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      尹连荣1941年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。在这段口述中，尹老人回忆了大饥荒时期及之后的生活。当时高各庄有人给生产队喂牲口，死了一头猪便煮来吃，他儿子抢着吃猪肉，结果撑死了。尹老人一家靠她爸爸在苇子地周围开荒捡吃的才不至于挨饿。尹老人结婚生了孩子后，因为营养不良没有奶水，只能花5块钱买了头羊，给孩子喂羊奶喝。
    - Zhang Zeying | 张泽英, 2010
      Zhang Zeying (b. 1943) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. His early life was quite difficult as his family was identified as landlords, his mother passed away when he was very young and his father was identified as a rightist during the Anti-Rightist Movement. In this interview, Zhang recalled the life from the Great Leap Forward to the Great Famine when clothes and food were very scarce. Everyone was assigned 17-jin grains per month and eating on the Production Team's canteen. However, because a large amount of the assigned portion was also for the 10 cooks working at the canteen, the foods were far from enough. Only catres had enough to eat because they either extorted or stole from the public properties. In 1958 there was a big harvest, so a large amount of grain were wasted. However, starting from 1959 when the harvest was not good and the stored sweet potatoes went bad because of low temperature, people started to starve. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      张泽英1943年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村村民，家庭出身是地主，早年母亲去世，父亲也在反右期间被划为右派。在这段口述中，张老人回忆了大跃进至大饥荒时期缺衣少食的生活。当时吃食堂，一人一个月分配17斤粮食，其中不少还要供给队里十个大厨，根本吃不饱。只有干部或偷或搜刮公家财产才不至于挨饿。58年粮食大丰收，大家吃饱饭就浪费粮食。59年开始粮食减产，存的白薯也冻坏了，挨饿的日子便开始了。
    - Zhao Guifang | 赵桂芳, 2010
      Zhao Guifang (b. 1926) was married into Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing when she was 20. In this interview, Zhao talks about her hardship during the Great Famine. Originally Zhao had five daughters and one son, but because the famine was worse in Hebei Province, Zhao's dad asked her to take one of her sister's daughters. Life did not improve until when the kids grew a little older so that Zhao could lead them to make mats for extra money while Zhao's husband went to work in the city.
      赵桂芳1926年出生，20岁嫁到了北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营。在这段口述中，赵老人回顾了大饥荒时期的生活。赵老人原来有五个女儿，一个儿子，大饥荒时期因为河北省的情况更严重，赵老人的爸爸便把她姐姐的一个女儿过继给了她。后来孩子大了些，赵老人就带着他们织席，再加上赵老人的丈夫在外头打工赚钱，生活得以有所改善。
    - Ma Shuying | 马淑英, 2010
      Ma Shuying (b. 1927) was married into Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing when she was 17. In this interview, Ma recalls the life during the Great Famine. During that time when Ma's husband went to build the Miyun Reservoir, she had to take care of six children all by herself. However, she still had to work at the production team otherwise they could not eat at the communal canteen. Later Ma led the children to make mats and hats for extra money. They were even disrespected by some neighbors because of their poverty.
      马淑英1927年出生，17岁嫁到了北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营。在这段口述中，马老人回忆了大饥荒时期吃食堂的经历。当时马老人的丈夫上密云修水库，马老人一人带六个孩子，但又不能不干活，不然食堂不给饭吃。后来马老人带着孩子靠织席织缇帽添补家用，还时常因为家里穷被人看不起。
    - Wang Shihua | 王士华, 2011
      Wang Shihua (b. 1926) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Wang recalls the life after 1949. After being demobilized from the army in 1954, Wang worked as the leader and then the secretary of the production team. He explains the operation of and differences between elementary and advanced agricultural producers' cooperatives and people's commune. To join the cooperatives, people had to pay a certain amount of money. If one did not have enough money, while poor and lower-middle peasants could borrow money from the credit union with zero interest rate, rich peasants and landlords had to pay the interest. Because of its reed field, Shaziying Village did not suffer as much as others during the Great Famine. Many girls made mats with reeds for extra money. No one starved to death but several old people died of constipation. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      王士华1926年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。在这段口述中，王老人讲述了建国以后的生活。王老人1954年当兵回来以后当大队长，后来当了书记。王老人解释了初级社、高级社、人民公社的区分和运作。当时入社得花钱，贫下中农入社钱不够，就由信用社无息贷款，但富农、地主贷款就得花利息。大饥荒时期沙子营比别的村强的地方在于村里产苇子，好多女孩子都靠编席赚钱。当时村里饿死的没有，但有老人因为上火便秘去世。
    - Jin Huilan | 金慧兰, 2010
      Jin Huilan (b. 1936) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Jin recalled the life from Civil War to the Great Famine. During the Sino-Japanese War, most men in the village did not dare to sleep at home, worrying they would be dragged to join the army. The Communist party forced the students to go to school, but at the same time they had to hide from the Japanese. During the collectivization, whoever did not join the People's Commune would be criticized and punished. When the Miyun Reservoir was being built during the Great Famine, all the men (except for the physically challenged) went to build the reservoir, while all the women had to build the roads, including those who were pregnant or had little kids to take care of. Due to the lack of food provided by the canteen of their production team, Jin ate all kinds of tree barks. Many people got sick, developed big bellies and eventually died. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      金慧兰1936年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村村民。在这段口述中，金老人回忆了从解放前到大饥荒时期的生活。抗日战争时期村里的男的怕被抓去当兵,不敢回家睡觉。学生们一边被共产党逼着去上学，一边得躲着怕被日本人发现。合作化时期虽说自由入社，但不入社就会被批斗。大饥荒时适逢北京修密云水库，村里男的除了瘸子拐子都要去修水库，女的就算怀孕或者带着孩子也得去修路。生产队食堂供应的粮食不够，金老人吃过各种树皮，好多人都得了大肚子病死了。
    - Zhang Fenglan | 张凤兰, 2010
      Zhang Fenglan (b. 1949) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Zhang recalls the life during the Great Famine when everyone had to eat at the communal canteen. During that time Zhang went to the communal canteen every morning to get thin congee for breakfast, and had only one bun for lunch. Zhang only studied at school for one and half years, during which time she always picked up firewood after class.
      张凤兰1949年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。在这段口述中，张老人回忆了大饥荒时期吃食堂的经历。当时张老人早上去生产队打稀粥，中午只吃一个窝头。张老人只念了一年半书，还得经常在放学后到外面拾柴火。
    - Meng Shiwu and Qi Tengyuan | 蒙士武&齐腾远, 2010
      Meng Shiwu (b. 1945) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. Qi Tengyuan (b. 1951) was married to Meng and therefore moved to Shaziying Village. In this interview, Meng and Qi recall the life during the Great Famine. Meng points out, because of the natural disaster, poor economy and the debt owed to Soviet Union, it was a very difficult time for the whole nation. People in the countryside lived on the work points earned through working at the production team, so they could not make much money. During the Great Famine, Qi was not married yet so stayed at home in northeast China. The life there was even harder. Her little sister had chondropathy because of malnutrition. Some people even dug mud in the river to eat.
      蒙士武1945年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民，齐腾远1951年出生，年轻时嫁给蒙老人，搬到了沙子营。在这段口述中，两位老人回忆了大饥荒时期吃食堂的经历。蒙老人指出，当时自然灾害，国民经济紧张，再加上要还苏联的债，所以特别困难。农村人靠挣工分，根本赚不到什么钱。大饥荒时期齐老人还没结婚，住在东北老家，生活更加困难，她的小妹子因为营养不良得了软骨病，村里甚至有人挖河里的泥来吃。
    - Zhang Qixiang and Wang Shufeng | 张启祥&王淑凤, 2010
      Zhang Qixiang (b. 1941) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. Wang Shufeng (b. 1941) was married to Zhang and therefore moved to Shaziying in 1962. In this interview, Zhang and Wang talk about the life during the Great Famine. Because of malnutrition, many people had edema, but thanks to the two jins of soy beans assigned for each patient by the government, no one starved to death in their village. Many people went to pick up sweet potato leaves and other edible things in the fields so that they could send them to places like Sichuan and Guangxi where the famine was worse. For every four jins of such "foods", the government would provide 1 jin of grains in exchange. Those days, because of hunger people would eat anything. Once a horse died in the village, so many people rushed to eat the meat. However, it was a sick horse so many people got food poison and were sent to the hospital. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      张启祥1941年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。王淑凤1941年出生，1962年搬到沙子营嫁给张启祥。在这段口述中，两位老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。那几年好多人因为营养不良得了浮肿病，所幸病人可以得到两斤黄豆补充营养，才不至于饿死。当时很多人去地里捡白薯叶等吃的，运到四川、广西支援当地，支援四斤政府就给一斤粮食。那阵人什么都吃，有一回村里死了一匹马，好多人去吃，结果都食物中毒送医院了。
    - Xu Yuzhen | 徐玉珍, 2011
      Xu Yuzhen (b. 1926) was married into Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Xu, suffering from memory loss, talks about her lifelong hardship. Her husband used to beat her all the time, and now her kids do not treat her well either.
      徐玉珍1926年出生，年轻时嫁到北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营。徐老人年纪大了，记忆力不好。在这段口述中，她讲述了自己的艰苦生活。以前一直挨丈夫的打，现在孩子也不好好照顾她。
    - Wu Zhanting | 吴占廷, 2011
      Wu Zhanting (b. 1935) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Wu talks about the life during Land Reform. Born as a poor peasant, Wu gained 3 mu fields during the Land Reform. However, he refused to move into a landlord's place when he could. According to Wu, the landlord that his dad worked for treated them very well, so during the Land Reform when the officials asked his dad to take food from the landlord he refused to do so.
      吴占廷1935年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。在这段口述中，吴老人回忆了土改时候的情况。吴老人出身贫农，土地平分的时候分到了三亩地，但让他搬到地主家时吴老人决定不搬。据吴老人回忆，他爸爸给扛活的那家地主对他爸爸很好，土地平分的时候分给他爸爸的粮食他爸爸也没有要。
    - Rong Shutang | 荣树堂, 2010
      Rong Shutang (b. 1920) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing and he was a teacher before retirement. In this interview, Rong recalled what happened before the Liberation and during the Land Reform as well as the later checkup. During the Sino-Japanese War, there were Red Eye Army who claimed to fight against Japanese but in fact were just bandits with secret relationship to the Communist party. The Communist party did not arrive in the village until 1937. Ever since then, they always held secret meetings with poor people in the evenings. During the Land Reform, many people had to forgo and move out of their own places for collectivization, but there was no standard criteria. Whoever refused to follow the orders would be beaten up. Many teachers, including Rong himself suffered ill-treatment during the checkup—wrongly accused, beaten up and even beaten to death. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      荣树堂1920年出生于北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村，退休前当了一辈子教师。在这段口述中，荣老人回忆了解放前的日子和当年沙营子村土改、扫房、复查的情况。抗日战争时期先有的红眼军，明着抗日实际上是土匪，但也和共产党有关系，后来37年以后慢慢开始有了共产党，经常晚上开秘密穷人会。扫房没有固定标准，被选中就必须搬走，不然就要挨打。复查期间很多教师也受到了不合理待遇，不少人被冤枉、挨打，甚至被打死，老人自己也挨了批斗。
    - Rong Baotang | 荣宝堂, 2010
      Rong Baotang (b. 1926) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Rong talks about the life before and after 1949. Instead of receiving formal education, Rong went to Beijing to work as an apprentice when he was 11. Later he went back home and worked for several landlords. In 1947 Rong joined the Communist party's army. During his 5-year army life, Rong participated in many battles and joined the Korean War in 1950. He got injured in 1952 and was demobilized after treatment. Upon arriving home, Rong worked as the production team leader and later was transferred to work in Beijing. Rong also showed his Demobilization Certificate in this interview. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      荣宝堂1926年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。在这段口述中，荣老人回忆了解放前后的生活。荣老人11岁就上北京当学徒，后来又给地主家干活，没念过什么书。1947年荣老人应征入伍，当了5年兵，打过不少仗，50年参加朝鲜战争，52年挂彩，疗完伤后荣老人便回国复员，在乡里当大队长，后来又调去北京上班。在这段口述里，荣老人还展示了他的复员证。
    - Liu Guiying | 刘桂英, 2011
      Liu Guiying (b. 1941) got married and moved to Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing in 1961. In this interview Liu recalls the life during the Great Famine. While eating at the communal canteen, once in Xiaodian Village, someone took a pack of white powder and asked people to sprinkle it on their buns. It turned out to be some kind of poison and many people got sick and were sent to the hospital. Because of poverty, those days people would try all kinds of ways to make a little bit more money. Liu's dad used to sell little handmade gongs made of willow branches. Liu's husband did carpentry work at the production team to earn extra money. Some people traded the assigned oil for money. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      刘桂英1941年出生，1961年嫁到北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营。在这段口述中，刘老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。吃食堂的时候有次小店大队有人拿了一包白面让大家搁在饽饽上吃，结果那是信金（一种毒药），好多人因此中毒住院。当时生活贫穷，大家想尽办法挣钱，刘老人的爸爸用柳条编成小锣拿出去卖，刘老人的丈夫在生产队里做木工挣一点钱，还有的人把发的油料卖了换点钱。|Transcripts for this interview and more may be available under the 'Documents' link above.
    - Rong Shuxun | 荣树勋, 2011
      Rong Shuxun (b. 1927) is a resident of Shaziying Village, Yang Town, Shunyi District, Beijing. In this interview, Rong talks about the life before and after Land Reform. In 1947 Rong was dragged to join the Communist Party's army. After spending 3 to 4 months in the army, he went home and that was when the Land Reform started. In June and July rich peasants and landlords started to be forced to move out of their own houses, and in November Decree on Land was carried out. According to Rong, people started to secretly join the Communist Party since 1947 and he also joined the party when he just reached 20.
      荣树勋1927年出生，是北京市顺义区杨镇沙子营村民。在这段口述中，荣老人回忆了土改前后的情况。荣老人47年被拉去当兵，当了三四个月，回家正赶上土改。47年6月、7月扫房，11月实行《土地法》。老人还回忆说，47年就开始有人秘密加入共产党，刚满20的他也在别人介绍下入了党。
    - Zhang Jiuping | 张久平, 2011